okay I'm going to do number seven we
because I guess I'll do some more
tonight okay but number seven as we will
see in the lamrim scripture I was in
Thailand you know descent in December
right and we were studying refuge so I
gave refuge vows for the first time in
many years
I think maybe 20 years or something to a
large group and everybody was excited it
took me many many nights to do the name
and you know I can get my sleep and
Stanley Adam was health they were all
going you know we didn't get sleep and
everybody was so happy and they got that
refuge vows and they got an explanation
of them and by the way we're going to do
that again in the scripture but
everybody felt like oh now I'm I got my
Buddhist name you know I'm a I took
refuge you didn't you did not okay
that's not resting okay refuge is when
you're sitting on the couch with your
wife or your husband and they start
yelling at you and you remember the pen
okay and and a bunker in vajay says in
the lamb rim okay you didn't get refuge
when Geshe Michael did the big ceremony
and gave you a secret name and you know
we all threw flowers or something that
wasn't the real ceremony the real refuge
vows ceremony happens on the couch at
home when your husband says something
bad to you or your wife says something
bad to you okay you're so lucky if your
wife saw something bad here because then
you can do the real refuge ceremony it's
right there that that that's the
moment to celebrate you know oh I took
refuge what happened
my wife yelled at me I didn't say
anything because I know she's coming for
me you know oh you you just took refuge
you just got your mouse who gave them to
you you did
[Music]
okay got it so that's the meaning of
this meditation number seven provoker
Buddha says the real ritual the real
refuge ceremony
you got your holy Garmin a m-- on the
couch it was stupid
okay and then you didn't answer okay
because you understood you didn't want
to see it again next week okay and you
understood the person called you stupid
wasn't there that is okay and and that's
that was your refuge ceremony that's the
point that Popovich is making in this
meditation so when you're doing
meditation number seven I would like you
to think about bad moments in your life
five and six are supposed to make you
happy
seven supposed to make you miserable
okay
Oh what's the most difficult moment I
had in the last few years
oh my it was that night when my my wife
you know told me how stupid I really was
you know and then you know I felt bad
and and I felt a little angry and I felt
hurt but then I remembered that even
that person was coming from me okay like
I don't know how I planted it it's
probably a million lifetimes ago because
I'm not that mean now but uh but I was
smart I took refuge you know she called
me stupid and I didn't try to explain
myself I didn't try to prove she was
wrong I just shut up I said you know I
got a peepee I'll be back
and I went in the bathroom and I sat on
the special place and I I spent ten
minutes thinking about how I planned it
done and then by that time I was calm
and I came out and I you know we
continued dinner and together and and I
took refuge and I had a refuge ceremony
in the toilet got it
okay so this meditation number seven
you're going to think about a difficult
time in your life when you did the right
thing you stopped yourself from getting
upset and you said this is coming from
me it's really hard with ex-wife's
ex-husbands ex-boyfriends ex-girlfriends
I mean ex bosses okay it's really hard
if you can do it with them you can do it
anybody okay so in this meditation pick
pick some of the most tense and unhappy
moments in your life with another person
and and forgive them because they're
coming from you okay let it go because
they're coming from you and then you
took refuge okay got it
forgiveness okay all right
you